Guide to the Theater collection, 1849-1964
Department of Special Collections
Theater collection,
1849-1964
Special Collections M0124
3 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Various sources.
Scope and Content
Correspondence by persons connected with the theater including actors, producers and writers, some articles, etc. on the history of the theater, a number of playscripts, drafts and prompt copies. ca. 1885-1954
Container List
- BARCLAY, ELOISE (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Theatrical Fragments from a Decade: 1850-1860. 1933carbon typescript with ms. corrections.
- BARRYMORE, JOHN. 1882-1942. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1. to Ray Lyman Wilbur. Apr. 19, 1926., T.L.S.
  - 2. to D. S. Jordan. Oct. 25, 1929., T.L.S.
  - 3. to Mrs. D. S. Jordan. Nov. 14, 1929., T.L.S.
  - 4. T.L. (carbon) to Mrs. D. S. Jordan to Barrymore. Nov. 23, 1929. not sent
    copy of Sargent portrait of Barrymore in Bender Room.
- *Booth, Junius Brutus 1849, Dec. 18to I. Sefton, A.L.S. (Box 1, Folder 2a.)
- CLARKE, B. H., COLLECTION OF LETTERS (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1. Oliver Larkin to B.H.C. Mar. 30, 1922with Apr. 2addition., A.L.S.
  - 2. Oliver Larkin to B.H.C. Apr. 14, [1922?], A.L.S.
  - 3. Oliver Willis to B.H.C. Jul. 15, 1937, A.L.S.
  - 4. A.P.C.S. Willis to B.H.C. Jul. 21, 1937
  - 5. is to B.H.C. Oct. 9, 1937, T.L.S. Wil
- CORNELL, KATHARINE. 1898- (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - to Mrs. M. C. Sloss. Jun. 18, 1932with cvr., T.L.S.
- CREEL, BLANCHE BATES (Mrs. George). 1873-1941. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - to Mrs. M. C. Sloss. n.d.with cover., A.L.S.
- DOUGLAS, WILLIAM (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - An Account of the London Theatres from the Restoration to the present time [1885]
- Daily Agustin Apr. 9, 1886A.L.S. to Mr. [Morrell?] (Box 1, Folder 6a)
- FILMS (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1. Feb. 7, 1936.Conference of National Board of Review of Motion Pictures. Relating Community Activities with University Interest in Motion Pictures Sawyer Falk., Carbon.
  - 2. Collins vs. Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer et al. Appeal and complaint for infringement of copyright, unfair competition to James M. Collins' Test Pilot.
- Forbes-Robertson, Sir Johnston (Box 1, Folder 7a)
  - 1. 1912 Jan. 24 :ALS to [?]
  - 2. 1928 Dec. 2 :ALS to W.D. Vincent (with cover)
  - 3. 1929 Jan. 6 :ALS to W.D. Vincent (with cover)
- FREIBERGER, EDWARD (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - to Agnes Ethel Tracy. Jun. 28, 1896., A.L.S.
- GERBERDING, MRS. ELIZABETH (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1. from Bertha N. Graham. [1911], A.L.S.
  - 2. from Joseph D. [Reding]. Jun. 14, 1913., A.L.S.
  - 3. om M. Meyerfeld, Jr. Feb. 3, 1911, T.L.S. f
- GRUBE, MAX (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Geschichte der Meininger (History of the Meininger). Carbon of original typescript of translation by Ann Marie Koller.
- HAMPDEN, WALTER (stage name of Walter Hampden Dougherty) 1879- (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - to Mrs. M. C. Sloss. Apr. 15, 1933and cvr., A.L.S.
- HERSHOLT, JEAN (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - to Dear Dr. Lyman Wilbur. Apr. 14, 1941., A.L.S.
- LANG, ANTON. 1875-1938. (of Oberammergau) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1. to Charlotte Knoch with note by Tony Schumacher. Both in German on postcard & typescript in German., A.N.S.
  - 2. to unknown. Oct. 8, 1909.in English., A.L.S.
- Payne, John Howard. Facsimile AMsS of Home Sweet Home & portrait (Box 1, Folder 13a)
- ROBSON, MAY (real name: Mary Robison). 1865-1942. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - to Mrs. M. C. Sloss. Feb. 7, A.L.S.
- SKINNER, OTIS. 1858-1942. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 2 to Mrs. M. C. Sloss. Apr. 12 & 15, 1932., A.L.S.
- THOMPSON, ISABEL IRVING (known as Isabel Irving). 1871- (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - to Helen Sutliff. n.d., A.N.S. and A.L.S.
- JACK, SAM T. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - to Friend Waldron and printed program., A.L.S.
- PLAYSCRIPTS
  - BROWNELL, ATHERTON (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The Unseen Empire., Copy of first draft. Typescript with some ms. corrections.
  - COTTRELL, H. D., DRAMA COLLECTION ( 1890s;handwritten copies with clippings and printed material inserted)
    - 1. Passion's Slave by John A. Stevens. Handwritten copy by Cottrell. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 2. The Golden Giant by Clay M. Greene
    - 3. Hazel Kirke by Steele Mackaye.
    - 4. & 5. Monte Cristo adapted from Dumas (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 6. Jean Valjean Act 6. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 7. Louis XI - Henry Irving's version translated from the French of Casamir Delavigne.
    - 8. no title - about a professor.
  - DE MILLE, HENRY CHURCHILL. 1853-1893 and BELASCO, DAVID. 1854-1931. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Men and Women 1890., Typescript [original?] with ms. corrections and stage directions.
      Stamped on several pages: Alice Kauser, 1432 Broadway, New York
  - ECHEGARAY Y EIZAGUIRRE, JOSÉ. 1832-1916. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - The World and His Wife. Adapted by Charles Francis [Nirdlinger] from El Gran Galeato. Prompt copy of Sir John Martin Harvey 1863- who produced the play as Slander in 1908., Typescript in English
  - EURIPEDES (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Medea. Translated from Greek by Melba I. MacLeod, adapted by Lolo Robinson and O. G. Breckett. Copyright 1950., Mimeograph copy.
  - [GILLETT, FRANK] (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 1. The Love for Three Oranges., mimeo copy.
    - 2. The House Bernarda Alba., mimeo with ms. corrections.
  - GRAY, HENRY DAVID
    - 1. The Way It Was., typescript. (carbon) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 2. The Call of Bohemia., mimeo and carbon
    - 3. And the Gods Laughed., typescript (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 4. A Superficial Girl., carbon
    - 5. Skyrocket, carbon
    - 6. The Shadow on the Sun., typescript (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 7. Rest Haven, typescript
    - 8. The People's Choice, typescript (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - 9. A Girl of Yesterday, typescript
    - 10. The Counterfeit Wife, typescript
  - HAUPTMANN, GERHARD. 1862- (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - The Beaver Coat. Translated by Bayard Quincy Morgan., typescript
  - JEFFERS, ROBINSON (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Tower Beyond Tragedy. Arrangement and by Edwin Duerr., 3 T.L.S. Typescript prompt copy with ms. corrections by arranger, printed program.
  - DICKSON, SAMUEL (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Stephen C. Massett. NBC radio script for Rickey's San Francisco Hour Nov. 28, 1954., 2 typed copies and 1 T.L.S. of _________ Rickey.
  - NICHOLS, DOROTHY (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - The Unpossessed., Mimeo with ms. correction and program.
  - PEASE, VERA JANE (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Scrapbook of her theater or recital clippings., 3 letters and a deed.
  - RISKIN, ROBERT (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - You Can't Take It With You, carbon.
  - SAVAGE, GEORGE, JOHN McRAE AND SOPHIE ROSENSTEIN (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Burnt Laurel. re: Christopher Marlowe., 2 type script copies.
  - SCHNITZLER, ARTHUR (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - 1. A Farewell Supper, typescript
    - 2. The Wedding Morning, typescript
  - TAYLOR, CHARLES (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - From Rags to Riches, carbon
  - TAYLOR, SAMUEL W. (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - The Square Needle, mimeo
  - Van Wyck, William. Lorenzo, Magnificent de Medici., Typescript with ms correction. (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Sheaan, Diana Forbes-Robertson (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - My Aunt Maxine: The Story of Maxine Elliott Galley proof, marked by Cam Stark for indexing of names.
  - Correspondence, 1961 - 1964 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    Gift of Sam Stark, May 31, 1968.
    - 1961, Oct. 14,Diana Forbes-Robertson Sheean to Samuel Stark re: her search for information about Maxine Elliott and J.P. Morgan's relationship., TLS
    - 1961, Oct. 16,San Stark to Diana Sheean with his ideas about Morgan and Maxine, and other general information., draft of letter
    - 1961, Oct. 19,D.S. to S.S. re: lunch with Elsa Maxwell, probability of a Morgan-Elliott relationship, biographies of her sisters and self., TLS
    - 1961, Oct. 23,S.S. to S.S. with suggestions as to when to write for moreinformation., draft
    - 1961, Oct. 26,D.S. to S.S. re: why Johnston Forbes-Robertson (D.S.'s father mentioned Maxine se little in his own book., TLS
    - 1961, Oct. 27,S.S. to D.S. re: Cole [Forter] and Catherine D'Erlanger, copy for an ad in Variety for Mrs. Sheean's book., draft
    - 1961, Nov. 6,S.S. to D.S. with an idea that a friend of his might have information on Morgan., draft
    - 1961, December],D.S. to S.S., Christmas card.
    - 1963, June 26,D.S. to S.S. re: his offer to do the name checking and indexing of her book., ALS
    - 1963, June 26,D.S. to Jim [Abagian] re: her index, progress with book, lack of warmth toward Maxine., xerox of ALS
    - 1963, July 12,Marshall A. Best, Viking Press, to S.S. re: his offer to check theatrical facts., TLS
    - 1963, July 18,S.S. to Marshall Best re: time needed for checking., draft
    - 1963, July 19,D.S. to S.S., TLS
    - 1963, July 24,Marshall Best to S.S. re: time galley proofs will be ready, TLS
    - 1963, July 25,D.S. to S.S., TLS
    - 1963, Sept. 28,D.C. to S.S. re: typing of book, corrections, misgivings., TLS
    - [1963, Sept.?],S.S. to D.S., draft
    - 1963, Oct. 14,Marshall Best to S.S., clean copy being sent., TLS
    - 1963, Oct. 23,S.S. to D.S., suggestions for improving book., drafts
    - 1963, Oct. 26,D.S. to S.S., her reaction to his criticisms., TLS
    - 1963, Oct. 29,S.S. to Marshall Best., drafts
    - 1963, Oct. 31,D.S. to S.S. re: corrections, reaction of London Publishers, TLS
    - [1963, Oct. 29?],S.S. to D.S., completed reading manuscript, suggestions, corrections.
    - 1963, Nov. 11,Marshall Best to S.S. re: reading the book from a theater point of view, adding a theater appendix., TLS
    - 1963, Nov. 21,S.S. to Marshall Best., draft
    - 1963, Nov. 12,D.S. to S.S., Manuscript off to printers., TLS
    - 1963, Nov. 21,S.S. to D.S. reply., draft
    - 1963, Dec. 12,D.S. to S.S. re: theatrical biography, list of pictures to be included., TLS
    - 1963, Dec. 13,D.S. to S.S., theatrical bio., TLS
    - 1963, Dec. 17,Edwin Kennebeck, Viking Press, to S.S., TLS
    - 1963, Dec. 20,S.S.[to D.S.] notes on theatrical biography, corrections., drafts
    - 1963, Dec. 22,S.S. to Viking., drafts
    - 1964, Jan. 10,Viking to S.S., TLS
    - 1964, Jan. 15,S.S. [to Viking], drafts
    - 1964, Jan. 17,Viking to S.S., TLS
    - 1964, Jan. 25,S.S. to Viking., drafts
    - 1961, Jan. 29,Viking to S.S., TIG
  - Clippings, Reviews, Miscelleneous. 1940-1961. (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Card file. Original index to My Aunt Maxine (Box 6)